[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome to the stowa i am
peter limberg the steward of the stoa
and there still is a place for us to
cohere and dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of this very
moment and today we're going to get some
culture war on
uh with paul vander clay
and for those of you don't know paul is
a pastor at livingstone's christian
reform church
in sacramento california and he
runs a popular youtube channel having
conversations with the likes of jordan
peterson jonathan vajo
and john for vaki so this is going to be
a standard
q a kind of conversation of the stoa i
think i see some new faces so how it how
it goes here uh
paul and i will have a brief
conversation he'll share his thoughts on
the the title of today's
talk if you have any questions throw
them in chat box
calling you to mute yourself if you want
me to read on your behalf let me know
because this will eventually go on
youtube
we have about 50 people rsvp'd but
half of that is here so we might have
more people trickling in
um so that being said do i have anything
else i want to say
no i don't so uh paul how's it going
today
yeah i'm your mute i'm doing well cool
uh so i thought um
before we dive into the kind of like the
theme of today maybe you can kind of for
people who just coming in
who don't know nothing about you like
who are you what is your maybe
world view uh and and what maybe maybe
some themes that have been coming up on
your youtube channel and
what's at the edge of your thinking okay
um well
that's my name is paul vander clay i'm a
minister in the christian reform church
of north america a
denomination that was established by
it's basically dutch reformed
there are about two-fifths of the
christian reformed churches in canada
and the rest in the united states i
have been a pastor here in sacramento
for 23 years before then i was a
missionary in the dominican republic
i for the most part have sort of
done my job quietly in my little corner
of the world
and about three years ago i
became acquainted with jordan peterson's
work
and i was i was fascinated by his work
and i was equally fascinated by
the following that he was developing
and when he started the biblical series
i thought this is something worth
jumping into
but by that point he had about 300 000
subscribers and it was already
kind of a big thing to jump into so i
thought well i'll just
add my two bits to the conversation on
youtube
and i hadn't really done much on youtube
but thought
i'll play with it and probably find some
conversation partners
like many who were excited about the
work of jordan peterson
i was having difficulty finding other
people who were watching
dozens of hours of him then i wanted to
talk about it with someone so i thought
well if i do a youtube channel
i'll probably be able to talk with five
or 10 other people who are interested
who somehow find my
channel but i was unprepared for what
would happen which was a lot of other
people found my channel
and i had way more conversation partners
than i ever had before
and so i started making i started doing
uh conversations with people i wanted to
talk with who were
talking about this and these were just
random people who would
contact me and want to have a
conversation so i started posting them
on youtube
because i found the conversations were
starting to repeat
and then discovered that there was an
appetite for those as well so
i did some commentary videos what i
pretty much today call monologue videos
it's basically my processing
what john verviki calls the meaning
crisis
i just finished this afternoon a
conversation with
cal zeldin who was raised roman catholic
and just
recently wrote a penetrating article
about
sense making he's been listening to idw
characters
and so i've found this a good way to try
to process
what i think is the end of modernity
now modernity has been dying for
a hundred years already but these things
die
slowly and perhaps where i fit into this
space
is uh jonathan pajot is an
eastern orthodox icon carver i'm a
protestant
and john vervicky is a non-theist and i
continue to believe that christianity is
a viable option
for people who are looking to escape
from the meaning crisis
and find sense-making yet
i think the church has continued to
change throughout its 2000 years
and will continue to do so the scary
thing is that
sometimes the church goes down dead ends
and you never quite know if you're
pursuing a dead end
until 50 or 100 or 200 years after
you've done it
so so i talk out loud on the internet
and some people listen and talk back and
that's what i do besides being a pastor
of a church
very right uh and i said beforehand that
i was some uh
obviously stoic but secretly a christian
not so secret
uh and i'm like um orthodox christian
actually uh so i got my my prayer rope
right here so
me and jonathan biggio have uh have a
fellow
hell company there um so i'm curious why
the protestant path
uh and i think i read your bio that was
something that you you fell into you
were
baptized into no yeah i'm third
generation minister in the christian
reform church so
this is my tribe this is my family a lot
of people listen to my videos and are
rooting for me to
change traditions but i have no plans on
it
i the protestant angle i i
brought that up in my conversation
recently with with jonathan and john
i'm not promoting protestant in it but
the protestant reformation i think in
many ways
is both at the root of the dawning of
modernity
and unresolved issues in the protestant
reformation
i think are driving some of the causes
of its demise and so
everyone in this current crisis have
things that they need to work through
usually because of their own tradition
if it's a very ancient
tradition like the orthodox well there's
the roman catholics have a lot to work
through right now and
protestants do as well in many ways the
different traditions work at different
speeds the orthodox a very slow speed
very ancient
roman catholic a little bit faster
they're a little bit newer protestants
are like
squirrels all over the place um stowing
nuts and different trees and often
forgetting where they are
and so uh for the title of the today's
talk was uh
um being a christian in culture war
2.0 um that's something i've written
about peter precaution had a different
take on it um
so i'm curious if you have like any
general thoughts on that
and um yeah maybe just any general
thoughts and i'll kind of have some
follow-up
i think culture wars are good places for
christians
and the reason i say that is because
christianity's
birth narrative happened in the midst of
a very fierce culture war
uh the um the jewish people
are an amazing group of people who have
resisted fiercely resisted assimilation
and were doing so in the midst of heavy
pressure from rome and
and hellenistic culture and into that
culture
war where just about everybody hated
each other
they could all romans and anti-romans
could agree
that the world was better without jesus
and so they killed him
and in some ways the rise of jordan
peterson
was directly a result of the culture war
because jordan had been making the same
kind of arguments for many years and you
can find them on youtube
but the man in the moment found each
other with jordan peterson
and i think jesus
is well he's the master and he's the
example
because of how he lived in the midst of
a culture war
the the the romans just didn't quite
understand him
the the zealots were probably deeply
frustrated with him
and the pharisees who should have been
closest to him in that culture war
eventually had a hand in putting him to
death but after his
uh death resurrection and ascension
many of those pharisees became
christians
of a sort so i think
even though christians will complain
about culture wars because they're hard
on us and they're tremendously
uncomfortable
i think christianity is uniquely suited
to a culture war environment because
it does the one thing that culture war
can't make sense of
it loves its enemies and
whenever you have a war that's the first
thing to go
because both your allies and your
enemies
will say uh this is the one rule that
must not be violated you must maintain
your tribe
and so how do you do that in the heat of
the culture war battle and maybe how do
you do that generally and how do you do
that personally
well jesus the the the heart of jesus
command is
love the lord your god with all your
hearts all mind and strength and
love your neighbor as yourself now the
neighbor goes all the way up to and
includes your enemies and
in the sermon on the mount which
is supposed to be jesus quintessential
uh distillation of his message people to
this day cannot agree on
what the theme of that message is but
right in the middle of it jesus makes
the observation
that god the father brings rain
and sun upon the righteous and the
unrighteous
and then jesus says be perfect do like
him
and so you if you if in the midst of a
culture war
you simply display weakness which means
you're just you're just the embodiment
of niceness and
all shucks can't we all get along that
doesn't
really work it's it's
loving someone you disagree with
and sometimes someone you disagree with
greatly now in this context we
immediately think of some political
rival in the culture war
but for many of us the people that we
uh love are also the people that
potentially we might hate
they might have been a a bad parent
they might have been an unfaithful
spouse
they might be a rebellious child they
might be a traitor to some
ideological tribe that you
care deeply about and are committed to
so how do you love that person and not
lose yourself
and i think it's that sort of thing that
we see from jesus because if you read
the gospels
he's no pushover he doesn't have a
problem denouncing things
white washed tombs he calls uh some of
his adversaries and again a lot of these
adversaries are the ones closest to him
in terms of beliefs yet this is the same
man that
at his um execution
asks praise for the forgiveness of his
executioners
while his body is dripping with the
mocking spittle of his enemies
that is a powerful thing and that is an
enormous
challenge which uh
you're looking for a meeting crisis well
if you try to walk that road
you will find meaning that's a pretty
cool reframe that the culture itself
is an opportunity to practice one's
christianity
yeah i think so i will look at the
origin story
under take take a look at the culture
war that jesus
was in the midst of and then read what
he does
carefully both well really that the side
that he's closest to
really wants to pigeonhole him so jesus
engage in our culture war when i was
so i was you know raised in the
christian reform church raised in a
preacher's
um raised in a parsonage you know the
son of a preacher
went to calvin college and calvin
college's
ethos was not so much you know really
try to contain the
covenant faithful but when you get to
college start thinking for yourself and
so i started reading the bible
really for the first time for myself and
i was immediately frustrated by all the
stories
about oh why are they why are they so
hung up on what he does on the sabbath
and
all these all these purity laws
well if you take a look at that culture
war all of these were the kinds
of the kinds of symbolic
virtue signals that one did to
position themselves on one side of the
war or the other
and you find jesus you know in some ways
sometimes
intentionally doing the impure thing you
read a story where he
he heals somebody on the sabbath and
it's like
well you couldn't have seen the guy the
day before or the day
after or you couldn't have done it
quietly in a corner you had to do it
right there in the synagogue with
everybody
watching just to tick them off and you
know the one story where the friends of
a paralytic drop
him down into the middle of a a a crowd
in a home
and he says your sins are forgiven he
could have said
take up your mat and walk and everybody
would have said well that's the script
he immediately goes for the sins and
it's like
he he he knows exactly how to poke them
but he doesn't do it in a culture war
way and he
he is an enigma to everyone including
his disciples
but yet for two thousand years we can't
seem to look away
so if you want to know how to live in a
culture war look at jesus
the only caution i'll give you is that
if you do what he did you'll probably
get what he got
which is dead so
if you don't believe in the second part
of the story which is resurrection
the first part might not make a lot of
sense
getting hung on the cross is the
ultimate christian practice
um so i have a few more questions but we
got a lot of uh
stuff in the chat happening um let's see
here okay david jacobs
you have a question if you can unmute
yourself and ask at the paul
david i guess i guess i'll just read it
um i wrote it down um
so i was fascinated to come on to this
talk uh
about the culture wars because i am
been watching it very carefully for the
last four or five years
um and i'm wondering how you explain the
um the vilification and the demonization
of the enemy by right-wing evangelicals
and the politically conservative
christian
nationalists i know i'm throwing a lot
of words out there you pick the one you
like the best
that's that's fine dave dave is a member
of our local sacramento meetup so
it's uh it's fun to get his question how
do i explain that
uh christians aren't always very good
at being christian and
they're just not that's been the story
right from the start
you know one-sixth of his disciples
betray him only one of those two was
restored
and when if you cl if you read the new
testament closely
you know there is a fierce debate about
what it meant to be a christian
and if you look at you know you look at
the story of the apostle paul
you look at stephen you know if you if
you thought that the
the the adversity against
christians were bad well amongst
christians it was terrible too
uh we i'm a protestant and so i believe
that christians are saved by grace
now i know that is often read as somehow
a dodge
but i being a christian
know that i'm often bad at it
and so i'm i'm thankful for a doctrine
that says
that my lord is patient with me and
whatever i
do whatever good i do in his name on
his behalf is done out of gratitude so
and and i think not to not to pick on
people let's say
to the to the right of me politically
but
you know what we've seen over the last
few years is those on the left um
know how to treat their outgroup poorly
too so i think that's a human thing
and ideally uh following jesus will
an increasing measure lead us to extend
grace to an ungracious world
cool uh dan feldman you had a question
yes i had a question um doesn't
the dualism inherent to
patriarchal monotheistic religions such
as christianity
fuel the meaning crisis itself
if you accept the terms patriarchal
depending on how you define it
i would argue that at least the meaning
crisis as
presented by let's say john verveiki and
even if we take it
as far back as we can let's say to the
11th century
uh christianity was still around 1100
years
before then i think a lot of the meaning
crisis that we're dealing with now
is a product of of modernity
and a product of
a lot of systems that suggest
that i have hours and hours of video on
this stuff
um that suggests that
we are not what we think we are whether
that is in a psychological frame that
there are things underneath us that are
pulling the strings that
our conscious self and this manifest
image are unaware of
or if we look at that in an evolutionary
biological frame
where i think i'm acting this way but it
is all the
tribalism of my ape ancestors that is
actually
manifesting itself out in these other
ways
so i wouldn't i wouldn't say that
you can place the meaning crisis as
we've been talking about at least in the
verveiki channels
on the to the feet of christianity
unless
you also place that um
unless you also place the scientific
revolution at its feet
and i would also argue that the
deconstruction
of the patriarchy and almost all of the
progressive ideas that we've seen
in the last few hundred years also find
their genesis and christianity
because in much of human history
out groups were simply enslaved and
killed
why does the victim
of the victim of
societal oppression gain status in our
narratives
and i would think that nietzsche spoke
presciently about it by saying
well it's that christianity that somehow
made everyone equal
and you have this jesus that dies for
people who think wrong
so that would be my answer to that
can i ask a follow-up to that question
peter
just one thing okay just one it i
i think the issue is is
i think you focused on the patriarchal
part of
of my uh comment and for me the more
prescient
uh uh word there is dualism
and i from my perspective is that
having some having a god be somehow
separate
or and also from my understanding i i'm
not
a christian or
anything for that matter i'm probably a
non-theist uh perhaps
um that the
the the disconnection from nature that i
think is inherent in
in christianity is is kind of the that
core
of that of that dualistic uh
division that's a that's a great that's
a great point and a great question
if you listen to brett weinstein
uh david sloane wilson
i think they make the compelling
argument that
human beings are not simply
biological creatures but fairly early on
a culture strain developed in us
that it's simply you simply can't
understand
a human being without those two tracks
both let's say the material genetic
track
and the culture track i don't think
humanity is going to get away from
dualisms
because of our two-track nature because
that culture track
is so has become so deeply embedded and
entwined
in the in the genetic
track that if you were to
if you were to i mean science fiction
plays with this sometimes
if you were to take a sperm and an egg
and try to develop it completely apart
from any human
contact first you couldn't do it because
you'd have to find a place devore
divorced from it but i don't think what
you would arrive at
is what we would call a human being and
i think that
that culture track is by virtue
of it being thought based
immaterial logos based
i don't think we're gonna ever get away
from dualisms
as human beings if you buy
the evolutionary um
biol biologist argument about what human
beings are
all right i can tell dan has another
follow-up but
do you want to sneak in and then i'll
i'll give you guys
[Music]
yeah and i don't want to yeah i guess my
point is that like for example with
taoism for example there's the yin yang
there the taoists can clearly saw poles
but they spoke of them as in dynamic a
mutual dependency
between them and i think that in much of
western civilization
and i think christianity played a big
role in this
um that the mutual dependence was not
emphasized
that that's uh i'll kind of i agree that
there's always going to be
an up and a down and this sort of thing
just like the taoists do but they
emphasize this dynamic balance
and interplay between the two that can
never be escaped
and i think in western culture we tend
to you know with
descartes we we decapitate uh
we separate uh we dissect we vivisect
and i think that's something that makes
us a bit different
uh in that sense and and what you're i
think what you're pointing to
is a lot of the conversation that i've
been having with john vervicky and
jonathan pajot
because and i actually think so one of
the things that i've
i've after watching jordan peterson and
sam adams debate i think part of what
happened
to the implicit definition of god
was that god got bifurcated and so
our assumptions about christianity have
sort of
and i think again the protestant um
reformation has a lot to do
do with this because with the move away
from
sacraments with luther
faith became a very psychological thing
and god became a very other thing
whereas if you say look at the angels
cry
in isaiah 6 holy holy holy is the lord
god almighty that's you know that's
about as that's as high as you can go
the whole earth is full of his glory and
so i think
part of what we see in the hebrew
scriptures is that
ironically christianity develops
as many have said somewhere between
jerus jerusalem
and athens but the jerusalem side
is the side that says of earth this is
our home
and so these issues these issues
have been debated broadly
throughout christianity for a very long
time
and you can still find them today i
think in fact
many conservative christians in the west
are functional gnostics
when you hear them say things like well
to be a christian means
going to heaven when you die well
christians in terms of the idea about
the intermediate state do believe
they'll be with the lord when they die
but in christianity our final status
is resurrected as bodily resurrection
so it's also ironic that with
a modern skepticism about the
resurrection of the body
i think that sort of distorts
christianity away
from the cry in genesis 1
of god saying of our embodied creation
in the flesh
it is good it is very good so but you
make a great point
i withdraw all right thank you very much
um limited to two follow-ups uh for this
session
uh okay we got laura laura's next
hi uh let's see if i can pull up my
question again
um so um in loving your enemies how do
you balance holding firm to your beliefs
and remaining open to the possibility
that your enemy
might have a truth to offer you and how
does a christian move past a sense of
righteousness of belief when necessary
it seems like many tribes in the culture
wars seem to struggle with this
i think it's i think there's a reason we
all struggle with it because it's really
hard
i first of all i think with jesus we see
he manages to do this
but one of the amazing things that we
see about
jesus and you can you can see it in the
old testament as well
in genesis 18 where
jesus seems open to the influence of
others and you would say well if the son
of god incarnate comes down
surely he should be talking all the time
and he wouldn't need ears
but that's clearly not the portrait we
see
with jesus so
i think it takes the development
of wisdom and this is one of the real
contributions i see john verveigh making
to the conversation
in and and and peter with the stow as
well because i've heard these themes
coming out of this conversation as well
that we must cultivate wisdom
and christians don't have a corner on
wisdom
if you read the book of proverbs
carefully in the writings in the old
testament you'll notice that
many of the proverbs come from
non-hebrew sources
the book of job which may very well be
the oldest book
in the bible many people believe
many scholars believe that the book of
job as we currently have it is an
adaptation of other wisdom literature
prior to that
even the stories such as genesis 1
and 2 i think are are
in conversation with egyptian and
babylonian
creation stories as well so if the bible
can listen to others and if jesus can
listen to others
and if god the father stands before
abraham which is the older of the two
because
you know very pious people said no
abraham will stand before god
but if god can stand before abraham and
abraham can plead the cause for sodom
and god will listen and negotiate with
him
well it should we shouldn't be so full
of ourselves to as
to be above god so no christians have a
hard time with this
because human beings have a hard time
with this because especially
when we get angry and culture wars tend
to do that
that anger fills us with a feeling of
righteousness
and then we tend to do most of our
damage so it's a great question
any uh follow-up laura
you're a mute no that was great thank
you
awesome uh aaron you're up next
hey paul uh great great to talk to you
i'm friends with mark hoffman down in
alameda and we were
all wonderful we're looking forward to
having you back in march i think it was
but
it's great to finally have a chance to
ask you a question um
i think of platforms like the stoa as
being a kind of church
it's kind of a weird decentralized place
where people meet up to sort of build
community and
engage in rituals and sense making and
uh you're engaging in this too with your
online platform on youtube
do you see christianity as moving more
into this kind of
strange online decentralized space
having kind of online churches uh where
people come together from all over into
little clusters like we're in right now
and do you see yourself as kind of being
a pastor
in this world right now do you have like
an online church do you think of your
platform as being
sort of an online christian church
i've recently started two new efforts in
my channel and i'm calling them living
stones online
because so many people can't go to
church physically and so we're going to
try to
do what we can to continue our community
online but the second effort i call
estuary
which i think when i listen to peter's
introduction to the stoa
uh this is a very estuary-like space and
what i mean by estuary
is that um if you have a walled garden
which in some sense the church
is and it rains in your walled garden if
you don't uh bless the rest of the world
with your water
no um you're going to establish a
reservoir
and so sacramento is right at the edge
of the
the great california delta and you're at
the other end of it
and so i think christianity has always
been in this space
it just hasn't done it well all the time
in in the in the book of acts
in ephesus paul rented a hall the
apostle paul rented a call
hall called the hall of tyrannus and
the book of acts describes him as
regularly meeting there and discussing
the philosophies and the ideas of his
day
he also did this on mars hill in athens
um i think medieval monasteries did a
similar thing
by you know why do we have
the the monastic movement preserved the
pagan writings of the ancient world
why would monasteries do such a thing
why didn't they
not only not burn the books but copy
them
you know so the church has the church
has done this i think
throughout its time but the church
always has two things to deal with
and in my tradition we call them common
grace on one hand which says
god speaks through creation and he
speaks through others
but also you know special revelation and
so the church has to
somehow maintain both the understanding
of an
of an antithesis but also the
understanding of
of common grace so i'm hoping that
my whatever efforts i can contribute to
creating an
estuary-like space will
con i think it makes churches better
to to talk and to listen
we the old as the old adage says we're
given one mouth and two ears
and churches sometimes major on the
mouth
uh and forget they have ears
thank you andrew you had a question
i'm i've copied and pasted it uh for you
if you can admit yourself yeah g'day
paul
and peter how you going um yeah my my
question was really just
your thoughts on the shift if you think
there has been one in the new atheism in
the last decade or so this is a bit of a
smaller focus question than the ones
we've had but um
somebody like a sam harris and i don't
know peterborough and people like that
you mentioned from time to
time on your channel um if i think back
10 years they probably were
more of an opponent someone to contend
with but
um in recent times um
they've sort of been on the same side i
guess
um so i'm just wondering what your
thoughts on you know what happened there
you know what what what took place
and uh just interested in what you've
got to say there
a very astute listener of my channel
that i've had a number of conversations
with he's a cardiologist up in idaho
uh noted to me that you begin to hear
from people often when
their assumed power in society is
slipping
and we've seen that from christians for
a very long time
all throughout modernity but his
observation was that
in some ways new atheism reached its
peak as they began to feel the
pinch of modernity receding
the irony of that recession is that
new atheists are increasingly finding
themselves
allied with christians who are making
assertions
about some fixed aspects such as human
nature
i think new atheists in some ways
have a more difficult time because
this losing this type of losing feels
new to them i mean for for many years
sam harris would go on stage and he
developed quite a following because as
some of the people who listened to me
have said every time sam harris would
sort of mock and expose christians
you know christians didn't have an
answer well
i had a conversation with james lindsey
on my channel
a year or so ago and i wasn't
really aware of sort of the split of the
church of atheism
between i would say classical liberal
atheism
and atheism plus and so that has
happened
and yeah it's produced some surprising
things
one day on twitter i saw peter bogosian
um tweet recommend
my podcast to his following and
i thought this is a strange turn of
events where a man who writes a manual
for creating
atheists starts recommending my podcast
either i've somehow lost my way as a
christian minister
or the world is changing and so
i'm more than happy to have productive
honest conversations with new atheists
and
obviously we have disagreement but you
know here i think
john vervicky is a real example
of someone with whom you can have
differences but have a
really productive honest conversation
and so
i you know again if christians are
called to love their neighbors all the
way up to including their enemies
well if um if new atheists are suddenly
warming up to christians
i i've got no problem with with uh
talking with them too
uh joe you had a question that would be
a good follow-up i
copied and pasted in the chat for you
joe you there i have a mouth full of
chipotle can you ask for me please
okay thank you it would be fun listening
to it but you know i will i will not
unchristian like to ask okay so what
does uh paul vander clay
make of human rights as a secular
replacement for all people being made in
the image of god
holland makes the argument that it's
just as faithful an idea as those found
in the bible and i'm inclined to agree
i think holland is right nicholas
waltersdorf who's a philosopher
was one of my professors at calvin
college has made a similar argument for
years
i i think it's
i i don't know i don't know where else
you
find respect for
low status outsider human beings
beyond what you find in
the imago dei or the image of god as we
find in scripture now that being said
the people of god have not always lived
that way
but it is i think anthropology has borne
this out
i was reading um i was reading a book
about the navajo
noting how navajo language just like
just about every other language of the
world
they had two categories the people and
everyone else jew and gentile citizen
and barbarian
this is completely common to humanity
and now suddenly and you can you can see
it in
jesus and you see the apostle paul
bringing it out completely that here
you have a god over all the earth and
all the peoples of the earth
belong to him not just a particular
ethnic group
so yeah i think human rights is directly
downstream from christianity
i think because of how secularity
unfolded there was a need
to to place it in this
um imagined religion free zone
but i think those distinctions and
definitions are also breaking down as
modernity recedes so
yeah i agree
um so i think this is
manus uh i copied and pasted your
question in the chat if you're going to
meet yourself
yeah um paul what is the most prevalent
criticism against christianity in the
culture war
from your understanding and what is your
response to it in light of christianity
having a
you know legitimacy in helping to
alleviate the cultural war
i i think the dominant modernist
strongest dominant modernist argument
against christianity has been the
problem with suffering
after and and this the formulation of
the problem of suffering
or the problem of evil arose
interestingly enough after the
destruction
of lisbon because that sort of that was
right at the beginning of the modern
period it really
shook the world before that
calamities happened you can read it in
the book of job there's an ancient
version of the problem of evil
but after human beings began to have a
vision
of our capacity
to manage the world in a better way
than nature did
once we had the kind of technology that
began to have an
impact on plague on
famine human beings began to say
hey if we can run the world
minimizing plague and famine war we
struggle with
but if we can run the world minimizing
plague and famine
why do we imagine that there's a
benevolent god up there
managing the world aren't we better
managers of the world than god
nature is read in tooth and claw
we seem to understand how to save a
human
life how to buffer our existence from
flood and
famine and would have said plague but
this gets into the postmodern complaint
which is well maybe we're not quite as
good at this as we thought we
were but i think that's the most
powerful argument and
and i very much understand when people
say i have difficulty believing in a god
because there's just too much chaos and
suffering in the world
and i don't imagine a good god would
allow all of this to happen
i think uh philosophers like alvin
plantinga
have answered the question well
but pastorally emotionally
if you're suffering it's a powerful
question
all right any thought on us yeah
just in terms of the the response i mean
um i feel like you touch on the first
part of that but i'm not
sure i connected with the second part of
the question which is
um you know what would your response to
be to it in in in the culture war so if
someone would say all right this is the
problem we have with the idea of
christianity this good god like
look at all the suffering um you know
why
why should we listen to christians like
what christians have to say
in this in the context of the culture
war like what would our response be
i think i think the the dominant
response of christians
has to be their lives
you know there's a great um you know
george orwell had a great response to
joseph stalin who was you know as
as we know now in the in the 1930s
starved the ukraine and belarus and the
name
of the utopian vision he was pursuing
and well if you want to
make an omelette you have to break some
eggs and george orwell
said show me the omelet
and i think that's the challenge
because the the power that we have
the power that we have
assigned to ourselves has filled us with
ambition and enthusiasm
but it seems we often over reach
and so i think the reason
i think the best answer that the
christian church can give
are the lives of its people and again if
you go back to
my first answer to david questions uh
christians
often fail and so
the real the real command that
christianity marches under is jesus
command
at the beginning of the book of acts um
you will receive power from the holy
spirit and you will be my witnesses
so the degree to which christians bear
witness to jesus
is usually the degree to which others
find
his answers compelling
cool uh paul you just
uh had a question have you got to meet
yourself uh okay let me get on the right
camera here um yeah so um hi paul um
i was raised as a pastor's kid in a
conservative baptist church in a small
town
in oregon so in that context hard right
politics and religion were very
intertwined
um it's very hard to separate them um i
was a pretty
self-aware kid but as i've become you
know 25 years
since leaving that that context um
become a lot more
you know scientifically socially um
globally conscious um and have left the
faith in that process and for me it's
it's hard it's hard to separate those
two progressions
um does that make sense so far oh yeah
yeah um so what are some other
frameworks that
uh and i assume i'm not the only one
what are the frameworks
of ways to think about that that
progression of
you know i've gone from this place of
being certain of everything i know
to this place of not knowing agnosticism
if you will but
um but in all other areas of my life um
and it's again it's very hard for me to
psychologically separate those i'm
curious your thoughts on that
yeah i i there are a lot of people
that i talk to who have stories like
yours
it was interesting to me that jordan
peterson
seemed to uh trigger and a lot of folks
with stories like yours a
reconsideration of christianity
i grew up in a home which was
you know conservative in terms
of christian belief you know the
resurrection the virgin birth
the resurrection of jesus uh the second
coming all of those things
but wasn't politically conservative
so i think a lot of people because these
things were together
they kind of associated it and it become
it had become a whole
and so a lot of people have sort of
deconstructed that
and and left other parts of it so
you know yesterday i did uh today
actually i posted a conversation with a
guy named jesse whose story
was very similar he deconstructed he's
since
found his way back i think
traditions every tradition needs
walls but traditions that rely too much
on the impenetrability of their walls
and i'm speaking about walls
metaphorically here in terms of
mental structures tend to be weak
when encountering other strong
traditions
and i think this has happened to a lot
of people
and i
i think as adults we have to exercise
stewardship over our beliefs
and look for the truth and work through
those issues and
probably be equally
serious about deconstructing new beliefs
as old
and so well there's a lot of folks with
stories like yours
and that's happening in the christian
church all over the place
and so i would just encourage i'm glad
you're here in the stoa
and encourage you to continue to pursue
conversations
with people who are wrestling with
similar things
so if peter if i could have one call up
yeah um yeah i think you hit on all the
all the the right issues and the things
i'm i'm dealing with and
it's really only been in the last six to
12 months i'd say
within the last 12 months that my dad
and i have even had
you know transparent conversations about
this it's mostly just been the elephant
in the room
which again i know i'm not unique there
um what are
what are some you know again
practical ways to open up that
conversation space with him when you
know it's clear it's it's a
major source of pain for him and i
understand that and care about that
yeah i think kindness is important
patience work hard on
work hard on not being easily triggered
and in all likelihood your father has to
work on that too
in my experience both of you probably
want a restoration of your relationship
it won't that might not be easy because
he's going to have to work through
some of his own beliefs and i i think
people sometimes try to short-circuit
this
ironically by pursuing
sort of a propositional approach
which is what they've deconstructed from
say dad if you'd only give up these
beliefs
well i don't think that's necessarily
true again
right at the heart of christianity is a
man
loving and dying for his enemies
if jesus can do that for his enemies
surely
it's a christian goal to do that for our
children with whom we have disagreements
and with our parents so i'd say keep
working at it
um and and you can't work you can't do
his work for him
so just work on your triggers
um you know when he inevitably says
something
that triggers you learn to forgive
and at that point as a christian pastor
i'd say
well if you're learning to forgive well
you're
you're listening to jesus because it was
jesus who said
you know jesus put such a high value on
forgiveness so
i have you know my best wishes are for
you and your father that that you can
restore the relationship and
and potentially have some
productive meaningful conversations
about why you've made the decisions that
you have
and he's also made decisions to stay
with his faith
and so odds are both of you can learn
from each other
all right uh let's bring
uh us home with joe's question joe if
you can ask your question and
meet yourself oh uh this is uh joe
pickens
hi paul good to see you
so i was listening to uh actually i
wasn't listening to the first part of
paul's question just now because i was
too busy formulating my own question but
i caught the tail end of it and it seems
somewhat relevant to my question which
is um
i see a necessity for christians many of
whom are very
close to me and who i care for deeply
because that was the
the protestant tradition that i was
brought up in um i see a necessity for
them to
take the plunge so to speak into
post-modernity and to integrate
modernity
with postmodernity and into a
christianity if that's what they want um
but there seems to be this huge dividing
line within my
own family and my community between
those who have taken that plunge and
those who have not
um and i feel like i'm in this
unique position and feel called in a way
to reconcile those
two tribes um
just if nothing else just within my own
family
and my community and i was wondering if
you can speak at all to that
dynamic between those two tribes and if
you have any experience with that
it's never easy and
how whatever good you wish for the other
side
human beings usually aren't capable of
necessarily delivering on those things
so i find again the central admonition
of christianity to love
to usually be the best pathway forward
figure out the best way to love both
sides
love has an amazing power to afford
credibility
to the person who is giving themself for
the other
these things take a long time and so
be patient i also believe
this work is difficult if you don't have
a vivid faith
in the sovereignty of god to
to accomplish difficult and hard things
in our midst in response to our needs
and requests
and so i recommend that as well
it sounds um and
there are so there are some ironies in
this generally speaking not always
many traditionalists have a theology
that affords
this type of sovereignty and power given
to god
uh people who are more progressive and
contemporary
often more skeptical um don't
have that resource to fall back
on to give them encouragement
so much of life is learning to suffer it
really is
and i find a
a a strong vivid belief
in god's goodness and sovereignty and
presence when we ask him
to be a tremendous help to
bearing under heavy loads and so
if you're going to if you're going to
endeavor to do a difficult thing
figure out the kinds of resources you
need
to endure the kinds of suffering that
that difficult thing will require of you
i don't know if that makes any sense
oh that is helpful thank you i i
especially liked the
uh what you said about loving each
side as best that i possibly can
and that giving a credibility to
uh i mean it's just you know
being the person that's at the center of
christianity sort of turns out to be the
solution to a lot of answers
yeah that's that's that's really the
program
but and and it's astoundingly scalable
can work in a public culture war and it
can work in a family fight
can work in a marriage can work in a
parent-child relationship
yeah awesome
uh yeah we uh so we're reaching our time
that we're
we have today um i thought that was a
really awesome
session paul i really really enjoyed
that uh
any um any closing thoughts for us
well i i
i'm you know i've been talking about
what i call estuary and it seems like
you're doing
a very similar thing here in the stoa
you're having meaningful
open-ended conversations across uh
culture war lines
so uh blessed are the peacemakers so
more power to you thank you sir um i'd
love to have you back on
at uh the store um if everyone in this
chat would like to continue with this
conversation you go to the discord
uh if you haven't signed up for
recording just go to the the rules
section give it a thumb a thumbs up and
you get access to the videos and you
just jump on a video chat
uh if people want to continue this
conversation to plug a few events
uh so we have dave snowden uh the the
founder and the discoverer of the
canevan framework and the chief
scientist
officer of uh cognitive edge uh he's
like the sense making
like superstar and he's he's the um
scent maker in residence of the store
for the month of
september the first session is tomorrow
that's
naturalizing sense making you can check
that out
and then uh paul we have a street
epistemologist
coming in next week using street
epistemology during culture war 2.0
uh that'll be interesting it should be
interesting we can set up an exchange
maybe
between you and anthony magna bosco
that's
that's monday september whatever
september eight is i don't know what
that is
at 6 p.m eastern time you can rsp there
and if you
like all these activities of the stoa
you can support us
on patreon at the link below
all right everyone much love and thank
you
again paul for coming out today my
pleasure thanks for having me